Guide to the Ed C. Brown Papers 1912-1964
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Ed C. Brown Papers
1912-1964
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 385, MtBC, us
Brown, Ed C.
1.2 linear feet
The Ed C. Brown Papers pertain to Brown's farming activities including: crops planted and prices; dairy cattle photos and breeding records; diaries of daily activities and weather; Huntley Project Irrigation District maps; reminiscence of working on the U Cross Ranch near Buffalo, Wyoming in the 1890s.
Biographical Note
Ed C. Brown was born in 1877 in Kansas to Mr. and Mrs. A.L. Brown. His family moved by covered wagon from Kansas to Iowa in 1889. He went to work at the U Cross Ranch near Buffalo, Wyoming in the 1890s. Ed was a ranch hand, and later became the ranch boss. He farmed south of the Yellowstone River near Ballatine and Huntley Project, Montana between 1912 and 1964.
The papers pertain to Brown's farming activities including: crops planted and prices; dairy cattle photos and breeding records; diaries of daily activities and weather; Huntley Project Irrigation District maps; reminiscence of working on the U Cross Ranch near Buffalo, Wyoming in the 1890s. The collection is arranged in six series: Diaries, Correspondence, Maps and Diagrams, Photographs, Printed and Literary Materials, and Financial Documents.
Series 1 Diaries, 1930-1961
Series 2 Correspondence, 1958-1960
Series 3 Maps and Diagrams
Series 4 Photographs
Series 5 Printed and Literary Materials
Series 6 Financial Documents, 1913-1959
This collection is open for research.
This collection was donated to Special Collections by George and Anne Stagg (niece to Ed Brown), Forsyth, Montana, February, 1965.
Huntley Project Irrigation District
Agriculture-Montana-Yellowstone County; Dairy cattle-Breeding-Montana-Yellowstone County; Irrigation projects-Montana-Yellowstone County; Ranches-Wyoming-Buffalo
Diaries-Montana-Yellowstone County; Reminiscences; Maps-Montana
Farmers-Montana-Yellowstone County
Agriculture; Environmental Conditions; Ranching; Montana; Maps; Photographs
- Diaries, Series 1
  Diaries written by Ed C. Brown, primarily covering daily activities and weather reports. A birth and death register of Brown's family, friends, and acquaintances is in Box 2, Folder 2.
  - 1930-1931 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1934-1938 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1951-1952 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - 1953 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - 1956-1958 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - 1959 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Birth and death register (Box-folder 2/2)
- Correspondence, 1958-1960; Series 2
  Personal correspondence received or written by Ed Brown between 1958-1960. The correspondence is mainly with W.W. Magee, reminiscing of working at the U Cross Ranch near Buffalo, Wyoming during the 1890s. Photographs referred to in these letters are in Series 4, Photographs.
  - Outgoing, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Incoming, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Maps and Diagrams, Series 3
  Sketches of Brown's field plots and maps for Huntley Project.
  - Sketches of field plots and crops planted, 1934-1960 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Huntley Project area and land owners, Montana, 1910; 1940 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Photographs, Series 4
  Photographs are of W.W. Magee and his travels, and Brown's dairy cows. Photographs are individually numbered, duplicates are given the save number. Photos vary in size.
  - #1-6 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - J.P. Magee, Parks, and Fred Hamilton, Hazelton, Wyoming, 1904; #1
    - W.W. Magee, 1954; #2
    - Magee's "modern sheep wagon", 1957; #3
    - Magee in the Tetons, 1957; #4
    - Magee by his office, #5
    - Will Kline, Henry Kline, and H.W. Magee in ranch yard, #6
  - Dairy cow, #7-17 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Nigger, 1925; #7
    - Lopsy, 1925; #8
    - Edith, 1926; #9
    - Edna, 1926; #10
    - Ella, 1926; #11
    - Ellen, 1926; #12
    - Erma, 1926; #13
    - Eva, 1926; #14
    - Flossie, 1926; #15
    - Frannie, 1926; #16
    - Pet, 1926; #17
- Printed and Literary Materials, Series 5
  Newspaper clippings, booklet, descriptions of pictures, and materials covering Huntley Project Irrigation District are topics in this series. Newspaper clippings include obituaries, advertisements, and other stories. The booklet known as the "Argument Settler" list facts on many topics. The hand written descriptions of pictures were done by Ed Brown. The pictures were donated to University of Wyoming Library and Archives by Brown in 1959.
  - Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Brown's Argument Settler (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Huntley Project Irrigation District papers, 1940-1959 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Descriptions of 25 photographs given to the University of Wyoming, 1959 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Financial Documents, 1913-1959; Series 6
  Ledgers, account books, investments, county tax records, and other materials related to financial matters of Ed Brown. Materials related to Brown's livestock and farm operations are found here. The memo books in Box 3, Folders 6-8 contain daily living expenses, cost of trips the Brown's took, and farming ideas and notes. Farm lease contracts are in Box 3, Folder 13, and land tenant's production and yields are in Box 3, Folder 14.
  - Ledger and land use records, 1928-1957 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Land payments and use, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Investments and Accounts, 1942-1964 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Ledger, Investments, and miscellaneous records, 1933-1956 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Account books, 1928-1934 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Account book, 1935-1947 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Account book and diary and family information, 1948 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Account books, 1949-1959 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Memo books, 1918-1939 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Memo books, 1942; 1946; 1947; 1956-1961 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Memo books, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Yellowstone County tax assessments, 1912-1925 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Yellowstone County tax statement, 1925-1959 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Federal land rent, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Cropping practices, USDA, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Land leasing and farm contracts, 1917-1951 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Crop yields, 1945-1960 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Miscellaneous financial documents, 1921-1940 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Dairy cattle breeding records, 1921-1940 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Certificates for shares of the capitol stock, 1913-1921 (Box-folder 3/17)